<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc4122 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2617 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml">
<!ENTITY dnssd SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheshire-dnsext-dns-sd.xml">
<!ENTITY mdns SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-mcroberts-remote-pairing-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Remote pairing protocol">Protocol for pairing networked devices to one another</title>
		<author initials="M." surname="McRoberts" fullname="Mo McRoberts">
			<organization>Project Baird</organization>
			<address>
				<email>mo.mcroberts@nexgenta.com</email>
				<uri>http://projectbaird.com/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="12" month="July" year="2010" />
		<area>General</area>
		<keyword>I-D</keyword>
		<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This document describes a protocol which allows two devices to
				establish a "pairing" relationship with one another, establishing
				a set of credentials which can be used to satisfy further
				authentication requirements.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
				As increasing numbers of devices are developed with network
				connectivity, it becomes desirable for there to be a standard
				mechanism for establishing trust relationships between
				individual devices: that is, "pairing" them.
			</t>
			<t>
				For example, consider a hand-held device, such as a mobile phone,
				connecting to a media device, such as a television. Because it is
				generally undesirable to grant unrestricted access to an unknown
				device (even across an ostensibly "private" network), some kind
				of authentication must be employed. Traditional username and password
				authentication tends not to be practical in this circumstance:
				rather, a process whereby a user can "pair" the devices with
				one another and (thus generate persistent authentication tokens)
				is more desirable.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification sets out a process by which this might be
				implemented. It requires that the "client" device (that is, the
				"remote" device) a display and some kind of input
				mechanism, while the "server" device features at a bare minimum
				a display.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Pairing mechanism">
			<t>
				The mechanism described here works on the basis of a shared secret:
				in this case, a randomly-generated code number (typically between four
				and eight digits in length) which is generated and displayed by the
				server and must be entered on the client in order to complete the
				pairing process. In subsequent authentication requests, supplied
				code number is used as a password, while a per-client server-supplied
				UUID <xref target="RFC4122" /> is used as a username.
			</t>
			<t>
				Before this can occur, the client must discover that the server is
				available for pairing: requiring users to enter hostnames or IP
				addresses is not generally practical, and so it would be preferable
				for client devices to perform automatic discovery of devices operating
				on the local network which offer a pairing capability. For this purpose,
				this document specifies the use of Multicast DNS
				<xref target="I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns" /> in combination with
				DNS-based Service Discovery <xref target="I-D.cheshire-dnsext-dns-sd" />.
			</t>
			<t>
				The complete process is described below.
			</t>
			<section title="Advertisement">
				<t>
					Server devices should advertise the availability of the pairing
					service using a DNS-SD service type <xref target="DNSSD-SRV" />
					of "remote-pairing". That is, registrations occur using the name
					"_nowp._tcp" and SHOULD by default be restricted to the link-local
					scope. Devices SHOULD make the service vailable via both IPv4 and IPv6
					and advertise the accordingly.
				</t>
				<t>
					Servers SHOULD NOT make the service available (and by extension,
					advertise) by default: they SHOULD instead require some kind of user
					action, such as enabling an option within a menu or pressing a physical
					"pairing" button. Servers MAY provide an option to users which allows
					continual availability of the pairing service.
				</t>
				<t>
					Servers SHOULD advertise a host name which is intended to be human-readable,
					for example "John's TV". Servers SHOULD allow the user to customise
					the host name, and SHOULD advertise the name consistently between
					services.
				</t>
				<t>
					Service advertisements MUST include a TXT record whose data is in the
					following format, given as Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) as specified
					by <xref target="RFC4234" />:
				</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
txt-record  =  "txtvers=1 uuid=" UUID " path=" path-absolute
]]></artwork>
				</figure>
				<figure>
					<preamble>A sample advertisement is shown below</preamble>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
_remote-pairing._tcp.local                IN PTR   John's\032TV._remote-pairing._tcp.local.

John's\032TV._remote-pairing._tcp.local.  IN SRV   0 0 80 tv234759.local.
John's\032TV._remote-pairing._tcp.local.  IN TXT   "txtvers=1 uuid=30146e8b-0d1a-47b9-825d-bebd7c23acaf path=/pairing/"

tv234759.local.                           IN A     192.168.0.25
tv234759.local.                           IN AAAA  fe80::223:dfff:feaa:4762
]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section title="Client initiates the pairing process">
				<t>
					The client connects to the server and performs an HTTP GET request
					on /pairing-request?device-name=&lt;name&gt;, where &lt;name&gt; is replaced
					with the client device’s “display name” (e.g., “Dan’s iPhone”),
					URL-encoded as required by HTTP.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Server returns a redirect response">
				<t>
					The server responds with 302 Moved temporarily and supplies a
					Location: header of /pairing-request/&lt;uuid&gt;, where
					&lt;uuid&gt; is a newly-generated UUID which shall be used to
					identify the client device to the server.
				</t>
				<t>
					The server shall store the UUID in some kind of local database.
					It shall generate a numeric passcode of not less than four and not
					more than eight digits, and store it in some way associated with
					the UUID. There shall be a flag of some kind associated with the
					UUID indicating whether the client device has successfully paired
					or not, and it shall not be set. The server shall also store the
					display name of the device associated with the UUID, as was
					supplied in the HTTP request.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Client follows redirect">
				<t>
					The client shall make an HTTP GET request to the URL supplied
					by the server (that is, /pairing-request/&lt;uuid&gt;).
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Server prompts for authentication">
				<t>
					When the server receives the HTTP request, it shall return a 
					"401 Unauthorized" response and include details about supported
					authentication schemes as per RFC2617. The server MUST support
					Digest authentication, but may support other schemes.
				</t>
				<t>
					The realm included in the WWW-Authenticate response header must
					be the server device’s own UUID. The client device may verify
					that this UUID matches that which it expected to receive given
					the Bonjour advertisement as a sanity-check.
				</t>
				<t>
					If it has not already, it shall display a message on its display
					indicating that a pairing request has been received from the client
					device. It shall display the passcode which has been stored and
					indicate to the user that they must enter it on the client device.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Client prompts user for passcode">
				<t>
					The client device shall indicate to the user that they should enter
					the passcode displayed on the server device.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Client makes request to the server">
				<t>
					The client shall retry the GET request to the URL supplied by the
					server, supplying authentication details as per RFC2617. The user
					name shall be the UUID supplied by the server; the password is the
					passcode entered by the user. The client stores the UUID and
					passcode for future authentication requests.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Server responds to pairing request">
				<t>
					If the passcode supplied by the client device is correct, the
					server must respond with a 2xx response code and marks the device
					in its database as having been authenticated.
				</t>
				<t>
					If the passcode supplied by the client device is incorrect,
					continue at Step 4.
				</t>
				<t>
					If the UUID specified in the URL is not present in the database,
					the server responds with a 404 Not Found status. The client should
					immediately abort the pairing process.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Indicate to the user that pairing was successful">
				<t>
					Both devices should add the other to a user-manageable list of
					paired devices and indicate that pairing was successful. The server
					will update its database entry for the client to indicate that
					pairing has completed successfully. Subsequent requests to
					protocols requiring authentication which properly supply the
					client UUID and passcode should then succeed until the user opts
					to un-pair the devices.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			&rfc4122;
			&rfc4234;
			&rfc2617;
			&mdns;
			&dnssd;
			<reference anchor="DNSSD-SRV" target="http://www.dns-sd.org/ServiceTypes.html">
				<front>
					<title>DNS SRV (RFC 2782) Service Types</title>
				</front>
			</reference>
		</references>
	</back>		
</rfc>