<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902"
   submissionType="independent"
   category="info"
   seriesNo="7"
   docName="draft-mcroberts-uri-dvb-07">

   <front>
      <title abbrev="URIs for DVB">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Scheme for Digital Video
         Broadcasting (DVB) Programme Resources</title>

      <author initials="M." surname="McRoberts" fullname="Mo McRoberts" role="editor">
         <organization>British Broadcasting Corportation</organization>
         <address>
        <email>mo.mcroberts@bbc.co.uk</email>
        <uri>http://www.bbc.co.uk/</uri>
      </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="A." surname="Adolf" fullname="Alexander Adolf">
         <organization>Condition-ALPHA</organization>
         <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gabelsbergerstrasse 60b</street>
          <code>80333</code><city>Munich</city>
          <country>GERMANY</country>
        </postal>
        <email>alexander.adolf@me.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.condition-alpha.com</uri>
      </address>
      </author>

      <date day="5" month="September" year="2011"/>

      <area>General</area>

      <keyword>I-D</keyword>
      <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
      <keyword>URI</keyword>
      <keyword>Uniform Resource Identifier</keyword>
      <keyword>DVB</keyword>
      <keyword>Digital Video Broadcast</keyword>
      <keyword>Digital Television</keyword>
      <keyword>Video</keyword>
      <keyword>Audio</keyword>
      <keyword>Multimedia</keyword>
      <keyword>Streaming</keyword>

      <abstract>
         <t>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes for broadcasting programme resources
            transmitted over MPEG-2 Transport Streams <xref target="MPEG-Systems"/> have been
            devised in their process of creating standards by the Digital Video Broadcasting Project
            (DVB), the Association of Radio Industries and Businesses in Japan (ARIB) and the
            OpenCable Application Platform (OCAP) to acquire current and future scheduled
            publications of broadcast media content from multimedia applications such as HTTP, MHP
               <xref target="DVB-MHP"/>, OCAP <xref target="OCAP1.0"/> or other XML based
            metadata.</t>

         <t>These URI are used to locate the actual digital TV, Radio or other multimedia broadcast
            programme services (i.e., channels or events) and also the audio-visual components
            related to that programme, for example an HTTP-based programme guide on the Web or other
            XML-based electronic programme guides in digital broadcast receivers.</t>

         <t>This document defines the "dvb" URI scheme for the benefit of the Internet community,
            given its definition as part of the Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB) suite of ETSI
            standards.</t>
      </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>
      <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
         <t>Standards governing televisions, set-top boxes and other consumer electronics devices
            have for some time been developed with the Internet in mind. The use of Universal
            Resource Identifiers (URIs) <xref target="RFC3986"/> is now commonplace, including for
            the purpose of identifying resources delivered by way of terrestrial, satellite and
            cable broadcasts.</t>

         <t>For this purpose, a URI scheme was developed as part of the <xref target="DVB">Digital
               Video Broadcasting</xref> suite of standards specifically for the purpose of
            identifying broadcasts delivered by way of DVB-compliant broadcasting systems.</t>

         <t>With the advent of digital broadcasting, digital multimedia broadcast services to the
            home, based on MPEG-2 Transport Streams <xref target="MPEG-Systems"/>, have been widely
            available in recent years. Each broadcast programme and component (i.e. audio-visual and
            generic data components) are identifiable within the MPEG-2 Transport Stream. Beyond
            digital broadcast, television and radio programmes can be delivered to receivers over an
            IP-based network within MPEG-2 Transport Stream packets.</t>

         <t>The Electronic Programme Guide (EPG) service for television and radio programmes which
            allows people to find and select programmes must be able to identify a given programme
            in a canonical form. As programme guides are increasingly being made available on the
            Web, and on-device programme guides are taking advantage of Internet connectivity, and
            as receiving devices are increasingly able to present programmes delivered both via
            digital broadcast and a variety of IP-based protocols, the the use of URIs to identify
            programmes is an obvious pragmatic choice.</t>

         <t>This document defines the Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes for broadcast
            programme resources over MPEG-2 Transport Stream <xref target="MPEG-Systems"/> for DVB
            services, conforming to the generic URI syntax <xref target="RFC3986"/> to aid in
            interoperability with existing IP-based services.</t>

         <t>The Digital Video Broadcasting Project (DVB) is an industry-led consortium of over 270
            broadcasters, manufacturers, network operators, software developers, regulatory bodies
            and others in over 35 countries committed to designing global standards for the global
            delivery of digital television and data services. Services using DVB standards are
            available on every continent with a total of more than 500 million DVB receivers already
            deployed. More information on DVB can be found on their website at <eref
               target="http://www.dvb.org">http://www.dvb.org</eref></t>

         <t>This URI specification is for a permanent assignment.</t>

         <section title="Transmission Scheme">
            <t>The audio, visual or private data components constituting a TV/radio programme
               ("service") are defined as elementary stream (ES) components. Several of these
               TV/radio programmes are bundled in a transport stream (TS) multiplex for delivering
               over a broadcast transmission network (e.g. satellite, cable or terrestrial). The
               distinguished unique number for each TS multiplexed packet, elementary stream
               component, transport stream and transmission network is assigned and transmitted over
               the satellite, cable or terrestrial broadcasting media, or over an IP network,
               together with an information table which describesthese assigned numbers, as
               described by the MPEG-2 standard <xref target="MPEG-Systems"/>.</t>

            <figure title="Programme Delivery Scheme in MPEG-2 Transport Stream" align="center">
               <artwork>
+---------------------------------------------------+
| BROADCASTING NETWORK                              |
| (e.g. Satellite, Cable, Terrestrial)              |
|    +---------------------------------------+      |
|    | TRANSPORT STREAM MULTIPLEX            |-*    |
|    | (e.g. channel)                        | |    |
|    |   +-----------------------------+     | |    |
|    |   | SERVICE                     |-*   | |    |
|    |   |  +---------------------+    | |   | |    |
|    |   |  | Audio/Visual and    |-*  | |   | |    |
|    |   |  | Private Data        | |  | |   | |    |
|    |   |  | Components          | |  | |   | |    |
|    |   |  +---------------------+ |  | |   | |    |
|    |   |    *---------------------*  | |   | |    |
|    |   |                             | |   | |    |
|    |   +-----------------------------+ |   | |    |
|    |     *-----------------------------*   | |    |
|    |                                       | |    |
|    +---------------------------------------+ |    |
|      *---------------------------------------*    |
|                                                   |
+---------------------------------------------------+
          </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>These elements are unambiguously identified in DVB systems through numerical
               identifiers: <list style="symbols">
                  <t>A <spanx style="strong">network_id</spanx> identifies a broadcast transmission
                     network. On satellite and IP broadband, typically one network_id corresponds to
                     an operator. On cable and terrestrial, where different radio frequencies might
                     be used in different regions, operators typically use one network_id per such
                     region.</t>

                  <t>An <spanx style="strong">original_network_id</spanx> is used where TV/radio
                     programmes are taken from one network and are re-transmitted on another one
                     (noting that a "network" in this context may simply be a different broadcast
                     region for the same operator). The original_network_id is therefore used by
                     receivers as a means of determining equivalence across different networks.</t>

                  <t>A <spanx style="strong">transport_stream_id</spanx> is used to refer to a
                     time-domain multiplex of several programmes carried in TS packets. One or more
                     multiplexes can be transmitted on any given radio frequency in a DVB
                     network.</t>

                  <t>A <spanx style="strong">service_id</spanx> identifies a TV, radio or data
                     programme within a TS multiplex. The number of programmes is limited by the
                     capacity of the underlying physical channel. </t>

                  <t>A <spanx style="strong">component_tag</spanx> identifies an elementary stream
                     (ES) of video, audio, teletext, subtitles, or other data within a service.</t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <figure title="Relationship of Network, Transport Stream, and Service" align="center">
               <artwork>
+---------+
|         |-------+
|         |       >+++++ Service 1 +++++
|         >  TS 1 |
|         |       >***** Service 2 *****
|  NET 1  |-------+
|         |-------+
|         |       >===== Service 3 =====
|         >  TS 2 >xxxxx Service 4 xxxxx
|         |       >##### Service 5 #####
|         |-------+
+---------+
          </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>The original_network_id is an attribute of a transport stream (TS). In the simplest
               case, all services originate from the network on which they are transmitted. In this
               case, the original_network_id of all the TS will be equal to the network_id, and this
               typically occurs on networks operated by public broadcasters. If one of the public
               broadcaster's transport streams is, for example, re-transmitted by a cable operator,
               the information about this stream would containe the cable operator's network_id, and
               the original_network_id of the public broadcaster.</t>

            <t>Thus, all assigned network_id values must correlate with actual broadcast
               infrastructure, whereas this is not required for original_network_id values which
               have a more logical basis. A globally active content provider may for example choose
               to register an original_network_id, and distribute pre-multiplexed transport stream
               to broadcasters, without operating any broadcast network of its own.</t>

            <t>The assignment of values for both original_network_id and the network_id are
               coordinated by the DVB Project. The DVB Project in turn has delegated the management
               of DVB identifiers to DVB Services S&agrave;rl <xref target="DVB-SVCS"/>. DVB
               Services maintains a public register of all assignments, and accepts requests for new
               assignments on their website.</t>

            <t>Due to the way broadcast transmission networks are operated (and, to an extent, the
               design of MPEG-2), some relationships exist between these identifiers: <list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t> Each TS is part of exactly one orginial_network_id (see above). </t>

                  <t> Hence, each TS is unambiguously identified by the tuple {original_network_id,
                     transport_stream_id}. </t>

                  <t> According to <xref target="DVB-SI-SPEC"/>, each service_id is unique within a
                     TS. Hence a service is unambiguously identified by the tuple
                     {original_network_id, transport_stream_id, service_id}. </t>

                  <t>
                     <xref target="DVB-SI-GDL"/> additionally requires that each service_id be
                     unique within an original_network_id. Hence, in areas where <xref
                        target="DVB-SI-GDL"/> has been made part of the broadcast profile, the tuple
                     {original_network_id, service_id} unambiguously identifies a service. </t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <t>During the process of performing a "service scan", a receiver will capture the
               identifying information contained within the transport streams and store their
               transport_stream_id, original_network_id and network_id, as well as the service_id
               values of all of the services carried within that transport stream. As each radio
               frequency channel is scanned, the receiver constructs a table correlating each of
               these tuples with the radio frequency channels and other modulation parameters, such
               that when it is required to switch to specific service within a transport stream, it
               can tune the radio receiver appropriately. Within the context of <xref
                  target="DVB-IPTV"/>, of course, there are no radio frequencies, however the same
               model of broadcasters, networks and services is maintained and the same identifiers
               are used with the same semantics.</t>

            <t>A DVB service is composed of one or more components. These are identified within the
               context of a service by their component_tag. A component can be either an elementary
               stream (ES) carrying video, audio, teletext, subtitles, or other synchronised data or
               generic data (see also <xref target="DVB-DATA"/>, <xref target="DVB-TVA"/> and <xref
                  target="DVB-MHP"/>). Each of these components is sliced into fragments and
               packetised in TS packets <xref target="MPEG-Systems"/>. All packets for a given
               component are labeled with the same TS Packet Identifier (PID), effectively providing
               a virtual channel within the TS for that component. The packets are time-division
               multiplexed according to each component's data rate requirements for broadcast.</t>

            <figure title="Example TS time domain multiplex" align="center">
               <artwork>
 ...|v|v|v|a|t|v|v|v|v|v|a|s|v|v|a|v|v|t|a|v|v|...
    |1|1|1|1|1|2|2|2|2|2|2|2|1|1|1|2|2|1|2|1|2|
---------------------------------------------------->
                                                time
 |x| : a TS packet                                                
 |x|
 
 v1, a1, t1: SD video, audio and teletext of service 1
 v2, a2, s2: HD video, audio and subtitles of service 2
          </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>In the above figure, all TS packets for "v1" would share the same PID value.
               Similarly, all TS packets for "a2" would also share a different PID value, and so on.
               The metadata describing the network, transport streams, services, and their
               components is transmitted within a TS using well-known PID values according to <xref
                  target="MPEG-Systems"/> and <xref target="DVB-SI-SPEC"/>. These metadata TS
               packets are not shown in the above figure for clarity.</t>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Digital Video Broadcasting URI Scheme" anchor="dvburi-scheme">
         <t>The DVB URI is defined by <xref target="DVB-URI"/>, and that shall be considered the
            authoritative source of the definition of the scheme-specific-part of the DVB URI.</t>

         <t>URIs employing the dvb scheme are URLs. DVB URLs may refer to any of the following kinds
            of resource: <list style="symbols">
               <t>A DVB service</t>

               <t>Components within a DVB service (such as an audio or video stream)</t>

               <t>An event (for example, a programme)</t>

               <t>A transport stream</t>

               <t>A file contained within a DSM-CC object carousel</t>

               <t>Interactive applications</t>
            </list>
         </t>

         <section title="Syntax">
            <t>This section details the components of the syntax. The syntax also makes use of
               components defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/> and <xref target="RFC5234"/>. These
               are not reproduced here for brevity. Future revisions of <xref target="DVB-URI"/> and
               related specifications may add additional syntax elements or otherwise extend the dvb
               URI scheme to support emerging DVB-based applications.</t>
            
            <t>This URI scheme is in conformance with the generic URI syntax <xref target="RFC3986"
               /> and uses the registry-based naming authority version of that. It takes the
               form:</t>

            <figure align="left">
               <artwork>
DVB-URL    = dvb-scheme ":" dvb-path
            
dvb-scheme = "dvb"
            
dvb-path   = ( "//" ( dvb-net-entity [ path-absolute ] ))
           / ( "//" dvb-app-entity )
           / path-absolute
               </artwork>
            </figure>
            
            <t>When the dvb-path part only consists of a path-absolute, the URI refers to a file in
               the default object carousel within the current DVB service. The "current" service is
               dependent on the usage context.</t>

            <section title="dvb-scheme">
               <t>The dvb-scheme name represents the transmission system using the MPEG-2 standard
                  in the digital broadcasting service in accordance with Section 3.1 of <xref
                     target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

               <t>In this definition "dvb" represents the DVB system which is based on <xref
                     target="BT.1306"/>, <xref target="BO.1516"/>, <xref target="J.83"/>, and <xref
                     target="DVB-IPTV"/>.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="dvb-net-entity">
               <t>A dvb-net-entity uniquely identifies an originator, transport stream, service,
                  event or component within the DVB system, either by way of numeric identifiers or
                  through the use of textual service identifiers (some of which are pre-defined,
                  while others may be advertised within the system). The dvb-net-entity may also
                  refer to a specific DVB carousel, or include a timed event constraint.</t>

               <t>The general syntax of the dvb-net-entity is:</t>

               <figure align="left">
                  <artwork>
dvb-net-entity             = transport-stream / service-entity

transport-stream           = original-network-id "." transport-stream-id

service-entity             = dvb-service [ "." component-set [ "$" carousel-id ]]
                             [ event-constraint ]

dvb-service                = ( original-network-id "." [ transport-stream-id ] "." service-id )
                           / ( "'" textual-service-identifier "'" )

original-network-id        = hex-string

transport-stream-id        = hex-string

service-id                 = hex-string

textual-service-identifier = reg-name

carousel-id                = hex-string

hex-string                 = 1*HEXDIG
            </artwork>
               </figure>

               <t>The dvb-net-entity, if present, may identify one the following: <list
                     style="symbols">
                     <t>A transport stream (through combination of original_network_id and
                        transport_stream_id)</t>

                     <t>A service, either through hexadecimal numeric identifiers or through in
                        textual form</t>

                     <t>An audio, visual, or data component within a service</t>

                     <t>A carousel contained within a component of a service</t>

                     <t>An event which occurs within a service</t>
                  </list>
               </t>

               <section title="component-set">
                  <t>The component-set referenced in the syntax above is used to identify one or
                     more components of a service and takes the form:</t>

                  <figure align="left">
                     <artwork>
component-set                     = component-tag-set
                                  / qualified-component-set
                                  / fully-qualified-component-set

component-tag-set                 = component-tag *( "&amp;" component-tag )

component-tag                     = hex-string

qualified-component-set           = qualified-component *( "&amp;" qualified-component )

qualified-component               = component-type "=" component-id

component-type                    = "video" / "audio" / "data" / "subtitle"
                                  / "teletext" / "dvbst"

component-id                      = component-tag / iso639-language-code
                                  / "default" / "current"
                                  / "hearing_impaired" / "visually_impaired"
                                  / "none"

fully-qualified-component-set     = fully-qualified-component
                                    *( "&amp;" fully-qualified-component )

fully-qualified-component         = "fqc=" stream-content-and-component-type
                                    "," component-tag
                                    [ "," iso639-language-code ]

stream-content-and-component-type = hex-string

iso639-language-code              = 3ALPHA
              </artwork>
                  </figure>
               </section>

               <section title="event-constraint">
                  <t>An event-constraint identifies an event occurring within a service:</t>

                  <figure align="left">
                     <artwork>
event-constraint = ( event-ref [time-constraint] )
                 / time-constraint

event-ref        = ";" [ event-id ] [ ";" tva-id ]

event-id         = hex-string

tva-id           = hex-string

time-constraint  = "~" time-duration

time-duration    = start-time "--" duration

start-time       = date "T" time "Z"

duration         = "PT" hours "H" minutes "M" [ seconds "S" ]

date             = year month day

time             = hours minutes [ seconds ]

year             = DIGIT DIGIT DIGIT DIGIT

month            = DIGIT DIGIT

day              = DIGIT DIGIT

hours            = DIGIT DIGIT

minutes          = DIGIT DIGIT

seconds          = DIGIT DIGIT
              </artwork>
                  </figure>

                  <t>An event may be identified by its event-id, a TV-Anytime tva-id, a start-time
                     and duration according to UTC, or a combination of some or all of the
                     three.</t>
               </section>
            </section>

            <section title="dvb-app-entity">
               <t>A dvb-app-entity is a specific form of DVB entity identifier which is used in
                  interactive applications, and takes the form:</t>

               <figure align="left">
                  <artwork>
dvb-app-entity   = ( "current" [ ( ".audio" / ".video" / ".av" ) ] )
                 / "original"
                 / ( ( "current" / dvb-service ) ".ait/" ait-abs-path )

ait-abs-path     = "app-root" / ait-application

ait-application  = org-id-part "." app-id-part [ "?" ait-params ]

ait-params       = "arg_" 1*DIGIT "=" *uric [ "&amp;" ait-params ]

org-id-part      = lowposhex-string

app-id-part      = lowposhex-string

lowposhex-string = lowposhex *lowhex

lowhex           = DIGIT / "a" / "b" / "c" / "d" / "e" / "f"

posdigit         = "1" / "2" / "3" / "4" / "5" / "6" / "7" / "8" / "9"

lowposhex        = posdigit / "a" / "b" / "c" / "d" / "e" / "f"
            </artwork>
               </figure>

               <t>DVB interactive applications are Java Xlets that are carried in the broadcast
                  signal. Terminals extract and then execute these Xlets. They are advertised inside
                  the broadcast signal in the Application Information Table (AIT). The
                  dvb-app-entity can thus refer to such application advertisements in its ".ait/"
                  form. In its other forms, the dvb-app-entity refers to a DVB service or components
                  thereof which are used in conjunction with the currently running application. For
                  further information, please see <xref target="DVB-MHP"/>.</t>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section title="Encoding">
            <t>Section 5 of <xref target="DVB-URI"/> specifies that:</t>

            <t>&quot;All characters not within the range of characters allowed in a URI must be
               encoded into UTF-8 and included in the URI as a sequence of escaped octets. An
               escaped octet is encoded as a character triplet, consisting of the percent character
               &quot;%&quot; followed by the two hexadecimal digits representing the octet
               code.&quot;</t>
         </section>

         <section title="Community Considerations">
            <section title="Context of Use">
               <t>The "dvb" URIs are used as references to resources in digitial multimedia
                  programmes, most often within the context of DVB itself: interactive television
                  applications use them in order to locate resources and to reference services and
                  programmes. These are typically broadcast via satellite, cable and terrestrial
                  systems, but may also be retrieved on-demand from a server via the Internet.
                  Providers of such broadcast services may e.g. reference programmes in the
                  broadcast from an Electronic Programme Guide (EPG) which is published on their
                  web- site. On another example, the metadata which is part of the multimedia
                  broadcasts can also contain such URIs to establish hyperlinks between broadcast
                  services. This might for instance include multi-angle video services (e.g. for
                  sports events). Users of suitably-equipped clients -- i.e. with a suitable tuner
                  card and software installed (Open Source tools including <eref
                     target="http://www.linuxtv.org/"/> and <eref target="http://www.mythtv.org/"/>)
                  -- are able to exchange such URIs (e.g. via an instant messaging service or email)
                  to provide each other clickable hyperlinks to multimedia content they deem of
                  interest.</t>

               <t>DVB has published specifications for the distribution of multimedia services via
                  IP unicast and multicast mechanisms. In this context, such URIs are usable in any
                  player client software (no tuner card required) that implements the respective
                  protocols and has the relevant audio and video codecs installed.</t>

               <t>
                  <list style="symbols">
                     <t>For example, a receiver connected to a local area network might allow other
                        devices to query it for information regarding the current programme or
                        service: in this context, a dvb URI would typically be the most
                        authoritative single identifier which could be used to to refer to that
                        programme.</t>

                     <t>Similarly, a web service can be implemented by a platform operator or a
                        broadcaster (or some party working on their behalf) which allows resolution
                        of dvb URIs - this would allow a device to retrieve web pages or other
                        content which relate to the current programme (or some other entry in the
                        device's Electronic Programme Guide).</t>
                  </list>
               </t>

               <t>Implementing such a system naturally requires some mechanism for devices to
                  discover an appropriate resolution service. DVB has developed has developed a
                  service discovery and selection (SD&amp;S) solution as part of <xref
                     target="DVB-IPTV"/>.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="Resolution Considerations">
               <t>The resolution process is determined through the development of DVB standards by
                  the Digital Video Broadcasting Project (DVB).</t>

               <t>Since the implementations envisaged cover a wide range of devices with quite
                  different access methods and capabilities, no single resolution or delegation
                  mechanism can be referenced in this document.</t>

               <t>Currently 2 client system classes are covered by DVB specifications:</t>

               <t>
                  <list style="symbols">
                     <t>A broadcast set-top box or other receiver which only has a unidirectional,
                        receive-only connection -- for example by way of a UHF radio receiver.
                        Hence, all DVB URIs need to be resolvable from the service discovery
                        information received within the broadcast stream.</t>

                     <t>A "home network end device" (HNED) which could be an IPTV set-top box,
                        networked TV or personal digital recorder with an Ethernet or WLAN
                        connection to a home gateway device.</t>
                  </list>
               </t>

               <t>Further device classes will be addressed as DVB standardisation progresses. The
                  dvb URIs must however remain valid. DVB will define appropriate resolution
                  mechanisms to ensure that DVB URIs remain valid for those new device classes as
                  well.</t>

               <t>For the two above example device classes, three mechanisms of conveying such
                  resolution information are currently defined by DVB:</t>

               <t>
                  <list style="symbols">
                     <t>Repeated, cyclic transmission of service discovery information as auxiliary
                        data in digital TV broadcast streams over satellite, cable or terrestrial
                        transmissions according to <xref target="DVB-SI-SPEC"/>, <xref
                           target="DVB-DATA"/> and <xref target="DVB-TVA"/>. Typically, this
                        information is collated and stored during a "service scan". It can then be
                        looked up at point of resolution, and the receiver may tune to the
                        associated frequency and if demultiplex the appropriate transport
                        stream.</t>

                     <t>Repeated, cyclic multicast transmission of SD&amp;S Records via the DVBSTP
                        protocol according to <xref target="DVB-IPTV"/>.</t>

                     <t>Unicast delivery of SD&amp;S Records in response to HTTP "GET /dvb/sdns"
                        requests according to <xref target="DVB-IPTV"/>.</t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Implementation Considerations">

               <section title="Considerations for resolution server software">
                  <t>With on-going development of DVB standards, DVB will establish requirements and
                     seek candidates for operating resolution servers as appropriate.</t>

                  <t>To boot-strap the resolution process, a DVB client needs to discover an entry
                     point (or set of) from which to obtain an initial Service Discovery and
                     Selection XML record:</t>

                  <t>
                     <list style="symbols">
                        <t>By default, the service discovery information is provided on the IANA
                           registered well-known port dvbservdsc (port number 3937) via tcp and udp
                           (see <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers">
                              http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers</eref>) on the IANA
                           registered well-known multicast addresses 224.0.23.14 (DvbServDisc on
                           IPv4) and FF0X:0:0:0:0:0:0:12D (DvbServDisc on IPv6).</t>

                        <t>As set forth in <xref target="DVB-IPTV"/>, a list of non-default Service
                           Discovery and Selection (SD&amp;S) entry points addresses may also be
                           provided via DNS based on the service location resource record (SRV RR)
                              <xref target="RFC2782"/>. The service name for DVB services is
                           "_dvbservdsc", the protocol may be tcp or udp, while the rest of the name
                           is the domain name maintained by DVB for service discovery. This domain
                           name is set to "services.dvb.org". The DVB organization will maintain the
                           services.dvb.org domain name for service discovery and new service
                           providers should register with DVB to add them to the DNS SRV list.</t>
                     </list>
                  </t>
               </section>

               <section title="Considerations for resolution client software">
                  <t>To obtain the initial Service Discovery and Selection (SD&amp;S) XML record, a
                     client must by default first join the IANA registered well-known multicast
                     addresses 224.0.23.14 (DvbServDisc on IPv4) and/or FF0X:0:0:0:0:0:0:12D
                     (DvbServDisc on IPv6) and try to obtain a boot-strap record from the IANA
                     registered well-known port dvbservdsc (port number 3937) via tcp and udp (see
                        <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers">
                        http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers</eref>).</t>

                  <t>To discover non-default entry points addresses, <xref target="DVB-IPTV"/>
                     defines that a list of Service Discovery and Selection (SD&amp;S) entry points
                     addresses may be acquired via DNS according to the service location resource
                     record (SRV RR) <xref target="RFC2782"/>. The service name is "_dvbservdsc",
                     the protocol may be tcp or udp, while the rest of the name is the domain name
                     maintained by DVB for service discovery. This domain name is set to
                     "services.dvb.org". So the lookup shall be either
                     "_dvbservdsc._tcp.services.dvb.org" or "_dvbservdsc._udp.services.dvb.org".
                     This requires that the terminal support an SRV cognizant DNS client and
                     according to the specification in <xref target="RFC2782"/>. The DVB
                     organization will maintain the services.dvb.org domain name for service
                     discovery. HTTP servers will be found via the tcp protocol method whilst the
                     multicast addresses will be found via the udp protocol method.</t>
               </section>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section title="Rights to Use Trademarks" anchor="trademarks">
            <t>Conforming to section 7.4 of <xref target="RFC3978"/>, the DVB Project who is the
               holder of various trademark and logo rights amongst others but not limited to the
               term "dvb", hereby grants IETF a perpetual license to use any such trademarks or
               service marks solely in exercising its rights to reproduce, publish and modify this
               IETF contribution. This license does not authorize any IETF participant to use any
               trademark or service mark in connection with any product or service offering, but
               only in the context of IETF Documents and discussions.</t>
         </section>

         <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
            <t>These examples make heavy use of the identifiers defined by DVB to identify entities.
               Please see <xref target="introduction"/> for an explanation of the concepts.</t>

            <section title="Referring to transport streams and services">
               <t>In the below examples, a receiver uses the identifiers in the URI to search its
                  internal database of radio frequencies and modulation parameters, which it built
                  during a service scan run. It uses the identifiers as keys to look up in the
                  various tables.</t>
               <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041"><vspace/>The DVB transport stream multiplex with
                        id 0x1041 and with original network id 0x233a. This might be used by a
                        broadcaster to provide an entry point to its service offering, without
                        picking out any of his services in particular.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf"><vspace/>The DVB service with id 0x10bf in
                        the DVB transport stream with id 0x1041 and with original network id 0x233a.
                        This could be used as the link behind a "watch this now"
                        button.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a..10bf"><vspace/>The DVB service with id 0x10bf and with
                        original network id 0x233a. This could be used as the link behind a "watch
                        this now" button. Note that compared to the previous example the transport
                        stream id is omitted. This is possible in areas where <xref
                           target="DVB-SI-GDL"/> is applicable.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://'MetroTV'"><vspace/>The DVB service named "MetroTV". Note
                        that as opposed to the previous example, the reference to the service's name
                        is not necessarily unambiguous and requires more contextual information to
                        be resolved. For "speaking" or "promotional" URIs, <xref target="DVB-TVA"/>
                        might be a more general alternative.<vspace/></t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Referring to service components">
               <t>In addition to referring to a TV/radio programme as a whole, it might be desirable
                  to be able to pick out specific variations of audio and video provided by a
                  programme. One could for instance always be interested in the video with open
                  signing, or in the audio for the visually impaired.</t>
               <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf.audio=fra"><vspace/>The default video stream
                        and the French language audio stream in the indicated DVB
                        service.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf.audio=qaa&amp;subtitles=eng"><vspace/>The
                        default video stream, the original language audio stream, and the English
                        language subtitle stream in the indicated DVB service.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf.video=default&amp;audio=visually_impaired"
                        >The default video stream and the audio stream for the visually impaired in
                        the indicated DVB service.</t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf.fqc=50B,3&amp;fqc=640,5,fra">The HD video
                        stream (stream_content 0x5 and component_type 0x0B) with component_tag 3,
                        and the French language ("fra") HE.AAC audio for the visually impaired
                        (stream_content 0x6 and component_type 0x40) with component_tag 5.</t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>

            <section title="References for triggering">
               <t>Applications might want to trigger on the start and/or end of TV/radio programmes.
                  The user might e.g. have set a flag on the programme, so that the receiver will
                  remind him when it begins, or might even automatically switch to the respective
                  service when the programme begins, and back to the previous service whe it is
                  over. Or a user might have selected a programme for recording. These scenarios
                  require that an application has some notion of the start and end times of TV/radio
                  programmes.</t>

               <t>Creating accurate recordings of broadcast content is a non-trivial task. For a
                  wider discussion of this, please see <xref target="DVB-TVA"/>. Although individual
                  service components can be selected for recording, all components of the service
                  should generally be recorded where appropriate. This would for instance enable to
                  use the original language audio instead of the dubbed version on special playback
                  occasions.</t>

               <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1004.1044;8fff"><vspace/>Event with id 0x8fff within
                        the indicated DVB service. A receiver would look up the EPG information for
                        the given service, and for the indicated event within that service. The EPG
                        information will contain the wall-clock start time and duration of the
                        programme as published e.g. also in print. Since the actual times of
                        transmission may be different, triggers should only be fired with
                        appropriate lead-in and lead-out times relative to the published EPG times.
                        Receivers can also use additional information in the EPG, in particular the
                        running_status. Not all broadcasters do however manage the running_status
                        reliably or in real-time.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1004.1044.audio=fra;8fff">French audio version of the
                        event with id 0x8fff within the indicated DVB service. The video would also
                        be implied if it is a TV service. See also previous example.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1004.1044;8fff~20100706T000315Z--PT00H31M17S"
                        ><vspace/>Event with id 0x8fff within the indicated DVB service, starting at
                        00 hours, 03 minutes and 15 seconds UTC on July, 6th, 2010, lasting for 00
                        hours, 31 minutes and 17 seconds. This form of the URI can be used to convey
                        more accurate transmission times for the content. The programme may be
                        advertised as starting at 00:00 and ending at 00:30 in the EPG. This
                        extended information in the locator can be used to get a much more accurate
                        trigger for the programme. The lead-in and lead-out times can be reduced to
                        the minimum needed to account for the skews of the local and broadcaster
                        clocks.<vspace/></t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Referring to data objects">
               <t><xref target="DVB-DATA"/> defines - among other things - an object carousel which
                  can be mounted as a file system. The data for this object carousel is transmitted
                  repeatedly.</t>

               <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf/doc/form.pdf"><vspace/>File in a subdirectory
                        of an object carousel, for which the root object is carried in the default
                        object carousel of the referenced DVB service.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb:/image.png"><vspace/>File in root directory of an object
                        carousel, for which the root object is carried in the default object
                        carousel of the current service.<vspace/></t>

                     <t hangText="dvb://233a..10bf.3$10a1240f/doc/form.pdf"><vspace/>File in a
                        subdirectory of an object carousel, for which the root object has the
                        transaction id 10a1240f and is carried in the ES with component_tag 3 of the
                        referenced DVB service. Note that compared to the first example the
                        transport stream id is omitted. This is possible in areas where <xref
                           target="DVB-SI-GDL"/> is applicable.<vspace/></t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>
            
            <section title="References used with interactive applications">
               <t><xref target="DVB-MHP"/> defines - among other things - how interactive
                  applications can make use of audiovisual or other multimedia services and service
                  components.</t>
               
               <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                     <t hangText="dvb://233a.1041.10bf.ait/1a2f.23b0?arg_1=Everest&amp;arg_2=Kilimanjaro">
                        <vspace/>Reference to the application with id 23b0, published by the
                        organisation with id 1a2f, as advertised in the AIT which is
                        transmitetd as part of the service identified by 233a.1041.10bf. In case the
                        application were to be launched, it should be passed two arguments; the first
                        argument is "Everest", and the second argument is
                        "Kilimanjaro".<vspace/></t>
                     
                     <t hangText="dvb://current">
                        <vspace/>The service currently selected by the Java Xlet via the
                        javax.tv.service.selection package.<vspace/></t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
         <t>This specification requests the IANA provisionally register the "dvb" URI scheme as
            specified in this document and summarized in the following template, per <xref
               target="BCP115"/>:</t>

         <section title="DVB Registration Template">
            <t>
               <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="URI scheme name:"> dvb<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Status:"> Permanent<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="URI scheme syntax:"> See <xref target="dvburi-scheme"/>.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="URI scheme semantics:"> See <xref target="dvburi-scheme"
                     />.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Encoding considerations:"> Conformance with RFC3986, no special
                     considerations.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:">dvb URIs are
                     used throughout DVB-compliant broadcasting systems, for example within Freeview
                     and Freesat in the United Kingdom. They are also used in TV-Anytime <xref
                        target="TV-Anytime"/> metadata where it relates to services transmitted by
                     DVB systems.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:"> None.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Security considerations:"> See <xref target="security"
                     />.<vspace/></t>

                  <t hangText="Contact:">
                     <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Name:">Mr. Alexander Adolf</t>
                        <t hangText="Title:">Chair - DVB TM-GBS working group</t>
                        <t hangText="Affiliation:">Condition-ALPHA Digital Broadcast Technology</t>
                        <t hangText="Address:"> Gabelsbergerstrasse 60b, 80333 M&uuml;nchen, GERMANY </t>
                        <t hangText="Phone:">+4915112722124</t>
                        <t hangText="Email:">alexander.adolf@me.com</t>
                     </list>
                  </t>
                  <t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
                     <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Name:">Mr. Peter Siebert</t>
                        <t hangText="Title:">Executive Director</t>
                        <t hangText="Affiliation:">DVB Project</t>
                        <t hangText="Address:"> 17a Ancienne Route, 1218 Grand-Sacconnex,
                           SWITZERLAND </t>
                        <t hangText="Phone:">+41227172717</t>
                        <t hangText="Email:">siebert@dvb.org</t>
                     </list>
                  </t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>

         <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
            <t>Section 7 of <xref target="RFC3986"/> describes general security considerations for
               URI schemes. The sections relating to reliability and consistency, malicious
               construction, back-end transcoding, rare IP address formats and semantic attacks all
               apply to dvb URIs. The section relating to sensitive information does not apply,
               given that dvb URIs do not contain authentication information.</t>

            <t>The security considerations of the Digital Video Broadcasting suite of standards in
               general are not covered in this document.</t>
         </section>
      </section>
   </middle>

   <back>

      <references title="Normative References">

         <reference anchor="RFC3986">
            <front>
               <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
               <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
                  <organization abbrev="W3C/MIT">World Wide Web Consortium / Massachusetts Institute
                     of Technology</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="R." surname="Fielding">
                  <organization>Day Software</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="L." surname="Masinter">
                  <organization>Adobe Systems</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="January" year="2005"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="RFC5234">
            <front>
               <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
               <author initials="D." surname="Crocker">
                  <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="P." surname="Overell">
                  <organization>THUS plc.</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="January" year="2008"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="RFC3978">
            <front>
               <title>IETF Rights in Contributions</title>
               <author initials="S." surname="Bradner">
                  <organization>???</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="March" year="2005"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3978"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-URI"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102800_102899/102851/01.01.01_60/ts_102851v010101p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI) for DVB
                  Systems</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="TS 102 851"/>
         </reference>
      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">

         <reference anchor="BT.1306">
            <front>
               <title>Error-correction, data framing, modulation and emission methods for digital
                  terrestrial television broadcasting</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="ITU">International Telecommunication Union</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="October" year="2000"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ITU-R" value="BT.1306"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="BO.1516">
            <front>
               <title>Digital multiprogramme television systems for use by satellites operating in
                  the 11/12 GHz frequency range</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="ITU">International Telecommunication Union</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="April" year="2001"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ITU-R" value="BO.1516"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="J.83">
            <front>
               <title>Digital multi-programme systems for television, sound and data services for
                  cable distribution</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="ITU">International Telecommunication Union</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="April" year="1997"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="J.83"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="MPEG-Systems">
            <front>
               <title>Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated
                  audio information: Systems</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="SMPTE">Society of Motion Picture and Television
                     Engineers</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="December" year="2000"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="13818-1"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB" target="http://www.dvb.org/">
            <front>
               <title>DVB Project</title>
               <author>
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-SVCS" target="http://www.dvbservices.com/">
            <front>
               <title>DVB Services S&agrave;rl</title>
               <author>
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="TV-Anytime" target="http://www.tv-anytime.org/">
            <front>
               <title>TV-Anytime Forum</title>
               <author>
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="RFC2782">
            <front>
               <title>A DNS RR for specifying the location of services (DNS SRV)</title>
               <author initials="A." surname="Gulbrandsen">
                  <organization>Troll Technologies</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="P." surname="Vixie">
                  <organization>Internet Software Consortium</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="L." surname="Esibov">
                  <organization>Microsoft Corp.</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="February" year="2000"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2782"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-IPTV"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102000_102099/102034/01.04.01_60/ts_102034v010401p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Transport of MPEG-2 TS Based DVB Services
                  over IP Based Networks</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="TS 102 034"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-TVA"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102300_102399/102323/01.04.01_60/ts_102323v010401p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Carriage and signalling of TV-Anytime
                  information in DVB transport streams</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="TS 102 323"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-MHP"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102800_102899/102812/01.02.02_60/ts_102812v010202p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Multimedia Home Platform (MHP) Specification
                  1.1.1</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="TS 102 812"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-SI-SPEC"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/300400_300499/300468/01.11.01_60/en_300468v011101p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Specification for Service Information (SI)
                  in DVB systems</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="EN 300 468"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-SI-GDL"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_tr/101200_101299/101211/01.09.01_60/tr_101211v010901p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Guidelines on implementation and usage of
                  Service Information (SI)</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="TS 101 211"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="DVB-DATA"
            target="http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/301100_301199/301192/01.04.02_60/en_301192v010402p.pdf">
            <front>
               <title>Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); DVB specification for data
                  broadcasting</title>
               <author>
                  <organization abbrev="DVB">DVB Project</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="ETSI" value="EN 301 192"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="OCAP1.0">
            <front>
               <title>OpenCable Application Platform (OCAP) specification, I16</title>
               <author>
                  <organization>CableLabs</organization>
               </author>
               <date/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="OCAP" value="OC-SP-OCAP1.0-I16-050803"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="BCP115">
            <front>
               <title>Guidelines and Registration Procedures for New URI Schemes</title>
               <author initials="T." surname="Hansen">
                  <organization abbrev="AT&amp;T">AT&amp;T Laboratories</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="T." surname="Hardie">
                  <organization abbrev="Qualcomm">Qualcomm, Inc.</organization>
               </author>
               <author initials="L." surname="Masinter">
                  <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems</organization>
               </author>
               <date month="February" year="2006"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4395"/>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="115"/>
         </reference>
      </references>
   </back>
</rfc>
