<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">
<!ENTITY dnssd SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheshire-dnsext-dns-sd.xml">
<!ENTITY mdns SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns.xml">
<!ENTITY linkhdr SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nottingham-http-link-header.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-mcroberts-nowp-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Now Playing (NOWP) protocol">Protocol for media devices to expose Now Playing information (NOWP) on local networks</title>
		<author initials="M." surname="McRoberts" fullname="Mo McRoberts">
			<organization>Project Baird</organization>
			<address>
				<email>mo.mcroberts@nexgenta.com</email>
				<uri>http://projectbaird.com/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="8" month="July" year="2010" />
		<area>General</area>
		<keyword>I-D</keyword>
		<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This document describes a protocol which allows network-connected media devices,
				such as televisions, set-top boxes and radios, to be queried for URIs relating
				to the content they are currently playing.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
				As media receivers (and other devices) such as televisions and radios gain the
				ability to communicate on local networks, a class of applications has arisen
				which depends, at least in part, on being able to query a media device for
				information about the programme or service it is currently playing.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document sets out a simple protocol which allows:
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						media devices to advertise the availability of this service to other
						devices on a local network; and
					</t>
					<t>
						media devices to be easily queried for "Now playing" information
					</t>
				</list>				
			</t>
			<t>
				Rather than be reliant upon the many different ways in which a piece of content
				might be described, the NOWP protocol instead relies on content and services
				having one or more identifiers -- in the form of URIs -- which can be relayed
				between devices and dereferenced as required.
			</t>
			<t>
				It is anticipated that implementation the NOWP protocol will often (although not
				necessarily always) form part of broader functionality to allow remote control
				and introspection of a device. For this reason, the NOWP protocol is based upon
				HTTP <xref target="RFC2616" /> and can co-exist with most other HTTP-based
				applications.
			</t>
		</section>	
		<section title="Conventions and terminology used in this document">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
				"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
				document are to be interpreted as described in "Key words for use in
				RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels" <xref target="RFC2119" />
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Advertisment">
			<t>
				The NOWP protocol is advertised to other devices on a local network using
				Multicast DNS <xref target="I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns" /> in
				combination with DNS-based Service Discovery <xref target="I-D.cheshire-dnsext-dns-sd" />.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document defines a service type <xref target="DNSSD-SRV" /> of "nowp".
				That is, registrations occur using the name "_nowp._tcp" and SHOULD by
				default be restricted to the link-local scope. Devices SHOULD make the service
				available via both IPv4 and IPv6 and advertise the service accordingly.
				The NOWP protocol specification places no particular requirement upon port
				numbering. Devices SHOULD allow the host name used in advertisements to be
				customised by the device's owner where possible.
			</t>
			<t>
				Service advertisements MUST include a TXT record whose data is in the following format:
			</t>
			<figure>
				<artwork><![CDATA[
txt-record  =  "txtvers=1 path=" path-absolute
]]></artwork>
			</figure>
			<t>
				Clients MUST disregard advertisements which do not include a TXT record.
				Clients MUST disregard advertisements which do not match the above format,
				including where the value of the txtvers parameter is not "1".
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Now Playing inquiry request">
			<t>
				Once a client has discovered a device advertising the NOWP protocol, it may
				connect to it in order to inquire as to the media currently playing on the
				device.
			</t>
			<t>
				The request takes the form of an ordinary HTTP request, where:
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						The Host request header MUST be specified as the fully-qualified domain name
						of the PTR record advertised by the device.
					</t>
					<t>
						The HTTP method used MUST be "GET"
					</t>
					<t>
						The request path is the value of the "path" parameter from the advertisement's TXT record.
					</t>
					<t>
						Clients SHOULD request that the connection is kept alive (via the
						"Connection: keep-alive" request header) where repeated periodic
						queries are anticipated.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Now Playing inquiry response">
			<t>
				Devices respond to the Now Playing inquiry request with an HTTP 2xx status
				code. Devices MAY include a response body, but SHOULD respond with a "204 No
				Content" status if none is included. Clients MUST consider any 2xx or 3xx status
				code as indicative of a successful response.
			</t>
			<t>
				For the purposes of the NOWP protocol, clients MUST ignore any response body,
				and MUST NOT follow URIs given in any "Location" response headers which might
				be returned.
			</t>
			<t>
				Devices relay URIs to clients by means of a "Link" response header
				<xref target="I-D.nottingham-http-link-header" />. The NOWP protocol
				specifies two Link Relation values which SHALL be used:
				<list style="hanging">
					<t hangText="http://projectbaird.com/ns/service"><vspace />
						This relation indicates that the linked resource is a service URI --
						that is, a URI which identifies a service which delivers content to
						the device, such as a television station or a podcast.
					</t>
					<t hangText="http://projectbaird.com/ns/event"><vspace />
						This relation indicates that the linked resource identifies a
						particular event, such as a radio programme or a locally-stored
						video file.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Devices MAY provide multiple URIs for a service or event but MUST
				NOT provide URIs for more than one service or more than one event.
				Devices MAY omit URIs for either current service, current event, or
				both. Devices SHOULD NOT include URIs with link relations of either
				http://projectbaird.com/ns/service or http://projectbaird.com/ns/event
				where the URI is known not to be meaningful beyond the device itself
				except where the device provides some other service which might make
				use of that URI in order to provide further information about the
				service or resource.
			</t>
			<t>
				Links with a relation of http://projectbaird.com/ns/event MAY include
				two additional parameters, described below. Devices SHOULD include
				these parameters if the relevant information is available, but MAY
				omit either or both of them.
				<list style="hanging">
					<t hangText="scheduledStart"><vspace />
						Specifies that the event, which was (or is being) received
						from a linear broadcast medium had a start time specified
						in the device's Electronic Programme Guide (EPG) as
						indicated by the value of the parameter. The parameter is
						a Datetime value in the format described below.
					</t>
					<t hangText="scheduledDuration"><vspace />
						Specifies that the event has a duration specified in the
						device's Electronic Programme Guide as indicated by the
						value of the parameter. The parameter is a Duration value
						in the format described below.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<section title="Datetime value format">
				<t>
					The Datetime format is a compatible subset of the combined date
					and time format described in Chapter 5 of ISO 8601 and has the
					format:
				</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
datetime  =  date "T" time "Z"

date      =  year "-" month "-" day

time      =  hour ":" minute [ ":" "second" ]

year      =  4 DIGIT

month     =  2 DIGIT

day       =  2 DIGIT

hour      =  2 DIGIT

minute    =  2 DIGIT

second    =  2 DIGIT
]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section title="Duration value format">
			</section>
			<section title="Service and event URIs">
				<t>
					The exact nature of a service or event URI is, in effect, an
					implementation detail, but some guidelines are given here.
				</t>
				<t>
					Service URIs are intended to allow the identification by
					devices other than the receiver of the service, and in particular
					by Internet-based applications which those devices might
					communicate with. A service which is delivered by way of
					DVB-T transmissions might use a URI which is made up of
					identifying values embedded in the transmissions themselves;
					a service delivered using RTP via multicast IP might instead
					be identified by the advertised URL of the SDP document
					describing the stream.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Examples">
			</section>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			&rfc2616;
			&rfc2119;
			&dnssd;
			&mdns;
			&linkhdr;
			<reference anchor="DNSSD-SRV" target="http://www.dns-sd.org/ServiceTypes.html">
				<front>
					<title>DNS SRV (RFC 2782) Service Types</title>
				</front>
			</reference>
		</references>
	</back>	
</rfc>
